Finding aid for the Lorees Yerby papers LSC.2242
UCLA Library Special Collections
Lorees Yerby papers
ca. 1950s-2000s
UCLA Library Special Collections
Yerby, Lorees
LSC.2242
6.4 Linear Feet (9 boxes, 1 flat box, 2 shoe boxes, and 2 tube boxes)
Lorees Yerby was a writer of short stories, plays, screenplays, and novels. In 1957, she and her husband Mike Dutton opened Coffee House Positano, located in Malibu, California. The collection consists of plays including Save Me a Place at Forest Lawn, short stories, screenplays, photographs, correspondence, and a small amount of research notes related to Our Fathers Trilogy.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIO MATERIALS: Audio materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Josephine Castelli, Pandora Castelli, Cynthia Dutton, Karen Dutton, Michael Dutton, Winston Dutton, and Carmen Spera; 2013.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9976804573606533
Biography/History
Lorees Yerby Dutton was born on January 9, 1930 in San Francisco. In July 1957, she and her second husband Mike Dutton opened Coffee House Positano, located in Malibu, California; the establishment closed in 1963. She wrote short stories, plays, screenplays, and novels. In 1963, her one-act play Save Me A Place in Forest Lawn was published. Yeby and third husband Bertrand Castelli produced the satirical film, Richard, about Richard Nixon in 1972. In 1976, she received a Guggenheim Grant for the Our Fathers trilogy (Nero, Mother England, and Abraham). Yerby later moved to Ocean Park, California, where she died in 1996.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of materials related to the career of writer Lorees Yerby. Included are short stories, plays, screenplays many of which were unpublished and/or unproduced, and a small amount of photographs, and correspondence. Additionally, there is a small number of photographs documenting Coffee House Positano, small amount of research for the project Our Fathers Trilogy and a small number of jottings and written thoughts by Yerby.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged into the following series:
Biographical Information
Coffee House Positano
Correspondence
Plays
Screenplays and Teleplays
Short Stories
Assorted Writings and Notes.
Authors, American -- 20th century -- Archives.
- Biographical Information, undated and 1978
  Scope and Content
  The series consists of photocopied and original clippings containing career and biographical information, handmade telephone book, and obituary for Michael Dutton. There is no specific arrangement to the series.
  - Lorees Yerby biographical materials, no date (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lorees Yerby press clippings, no date (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mike Dutton obituary from Telegram Tribute, no date (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Slides (from box labeled Our gang), 1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Telephone book (handmade), no date (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Coffee House Positano, undated
  The series consists of one file of photographs and a mailer for Coffee House Positano.
  - Coffee House Positano related photographs and mailer, no date (Box 1, File 6)
- Correspondence, undated, 1951, 1962-1964, and 1979-ca. 1990s
  The series consists of photocopied and originals letters to and from Lorees Yerby. Among the correspondents are Bertrand Castelli, Mike Dutton, David Walker, and Audrey Wood among others. The series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Letters from Lorees Yerby, 1951, 1992, and no date (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letters from Lorees Yerby to Mike Dutton, no date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letters related to Bertrand Castelli, 1988-1990 and no date (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Letters to Lorees Yerby, 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters to Lorees Yerby from David Walker, 1990s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters to Lorees Yerby from Audrey Wood, 1962-1964, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Plays, 1954-1955, 1961, 1973, and 1988-2002
  The bulk of the series consists of scripts. Additionally included is a small number of letters, contracts, and royalty payments related to Yerby's work Save Me a Place at Forest Lawn, some of which documents attempts for its production after Yerby's death. The series is arranged in alphabetically by project title.
  - Archesporium, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - How to Make the Sun Rise, 1973, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Golden Bull of Boredom, [1955?] (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Last Minstrel, [1955?] (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - A Modern Ecstasy, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Money Talks, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Penchant for Listening (third act), [1961?] (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Ragged Dick (5 folders), c. 1964 (Box 4, Folder 16-20)
  - Save Me a Place at Forest Lawn (14 folders), 1986-2002 (Box 2, Folder 1-12, Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    Typescripts, contracts, treatments for television, and correspondence.
  - Sorrow's Kiss, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Snow White, The Opera, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Screenplays and Teleplays, undated, 1972, 1977, and ca. 1980s-1990s
  The bulk of the series consists of scripts representing projects written Yerby, including the Our Fathers trilogy and Richard among others. Additionally included is a small amount of research materials and audio visual materials and a small number of letters, contracts, and royalty payments. The series is arranged in alphabetically by project title. Audio visual materials are restricted and require advance notice for use.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS AUDIO MATERIALS: Audio materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audio materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Abraham (Part Three of Our Fathers Trilogy) (2 folders), ca. 1994 (Box 6, Folder 13-14, Box 13, Box 11, Box 14)
  - Devils, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Farewell, Youth (3 folders), no date (Box 5, Folder 1, Box 4, Folder 21, Folder 13)
  - Mr. Lincoln's War, no date (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Mother England (Part Two of Our Fathers Trilogy) (7 folders), 1989 (Box 6, Folder 6-12, Box 9, Box 13, Box 11)
  - Nero (Part One of Our Fathers Trilogy) (15 folders, 18 casette tapes, index cards, sheet music, and 1 roll), 1977, 1986-1988 (Box 9, Box 10, Box 11, Box 1, Folder 10, Box 6, Folder 1-4, Box 5, Folder 2-11)
    Audio materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audio materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Untitled filmplay (Tentative Title: To Walk a Plank), no date (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Pickpocket Lover, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Richard (1 folder and cd and vhs), 1972 (Box 12, Box 7, Folder 5)
- Short Stories, 1971-1975, 1980-1982, and 1988-1992
  The series consists of published and unpublished short stories and a small number of letters and contracts. Included are The Boy Who Would Be Emperor, A Fairy Tale, and Lillian among others. The series is arranged in alphabetically by project title.
  - All Die Laughing, no date (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - April's Fool, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - At The Sidewalk Cafe, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Beijing Boogie or Mao's Last Nightmare, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Boy Meets Girl, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - The Boy Who Would Be Emperor in Cosmopolitan Magazine, 1974 Jul (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Brenda Starr and Her Quest for the Father of Rock, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Ciao, Tita (4 copies), 1974, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - City Life, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Crime and Impotence, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - A Day In the Sex of Life, no date (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Dying in the East Sixties, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - A Fairy Tale in Cosmopolitan Magazine, 1974 Nov (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - The Faithful Listen to the Gravity of Love, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Flight of the Bumble Bee, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - For Yule, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Gentlemen Prefer Bombs (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Letters from Mississippi (2 copies), 1991 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Lillian: Or One Week in the Life of a Good Secretary in Cosmopolitan Magazine, 1976 Jan (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - A Manifesto for the Majority, no date (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - A Modest Proposal, no date (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - A Monologue on the Self, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - One At A Time, Please, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Only Shadows Know, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Past Redemption: A Story for Heavy Drinkers, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Rape of the Soul and Cry of the Dead, no date (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - A Soldier's Story, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Soul Pudding, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - The Tao of Cancer, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Wise Men Never Try, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Wow Me, no date (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Assorted Writings and Notes, undated and 1959-1995
  The series consists of random writings, jottings, and notes. Additionally included is what appears to be drafts of letters written by Yerby. The files are arranged in alphabetically by loose geographic location where the writings originated.
  - Arcadia Terrace, 1976-1979 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Assorted writings and notes, c. 1959-1960 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Assorted writings and notes, c. 1990s (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Biloxi, Mississippi, 1991-1992 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Coming Comic California, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Copyright registrations for various works, c. early 1960s (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - The Culpepper Tree writings and notes, c. early 1960s (Box 7, File 15)
  - Dracula notes, no date (Box 7undated and 1978, Folder 4)
  - Emotional Alphabet (The), no date (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Hyde Street, 1983-1985 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Journal, 1987-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Pass Christian, Mississippi, 1974-1975 (Box 7, Box 19)
  - Princeton, 1985-1986 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Rancho Santa Fe Ashville, 1981-1982 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Riviera Avenue, 1986-1988 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Robert Briffault, The Mothers, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - San Francisco, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Second Street, 1989-1990 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Second Street, 1994-1995 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Shangri-La, 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Tao in the Kitchen, no date (Box 7, Folder 10)